Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
I probably can't quit the money transfer scam anymore.
Nie mogę się już wycofać z robienia przekrętów.
That's right. No matter what happens...
Co by się nie działo...
I can't quit.
Nie mogę.
Mom?
Mamo?
Makoto. Explain this.
Makoto. Wyjaśnij mi to.
Well, you see,
Widzisz,
my work is kind of special, so...
mam dość szczególną pracę.
Wait. Why were you searching my room?
Czego szukałaś w moim pokoju?
I went through your computer, too.
Komputer też przejrzałam.
-What? How? -Your password is your birthday, right?
- Jak? - Twoje hasło to twoja data urodzenia.
I couldn't believe it. It's filled with plans for scamming people.
Nie do wiary. Oszukujesz ludzi.
So you paid for your dad's treatment and your student loans
Opłaciłeś leczenie taty i studia
with the money you stole from the elderly?
z pieniędzy, które ukradłeś staruszkom?
That's right.
Tak.
If I had a regular job, I'd be used like a slave
W normalnej pracy harowałbym jak wół,
and make virtually nothing.
a nic bym nie zarobił.
Now I'm rich,
Dzięki przekrętom
thanks to scamming.
jestem bogaty.
What are you going to do now?
Co teraz zrobisz?
I plan to quit...
Zamierzam to rzucić.
"Plan to"?
Zamierzasz?
I'm in charge of something big now. I have to finish that first.
Odpowiadam za duży projekt. Muszę go dokończyć.
You can't get out now?
Nie możesz zrezygnować?
This isn't a game. If I quit now, they'll kill me!
To nie zabawa. Zabiliby mnie.
-Let's go to the police. -The police?
- Chodźmy na policję. - Na policję?
We can't. They'd kill all of us.
Zabiliby nas.
We can't, no matter what. I can't turn myself in--
Nie możemy. Nie pójdę...
Calm down!
Uspokój się!
The truth is, I heard that you were acting strange
Misaki mówiła,
from Misaki-chan.
że dziwnie się zachowujesz.
Misaki?
Misaki?
I thought about a lot of things while I was waiting for you.
Wiele rozmyślałam, czekając na ciebie.
"What would your dad say?" Things like that.
O tym, co by powiedział tata.
When will you finish that "big job"?
Kiedy skończysz ten „projekt”?
What?
Co?
I'm asking you about your job situation.
Pytam o twoją pracę.
Well...
Cóż...
Our goal is really high, so I'm not sure if we'll reach it...
Mamy spory cel, nie wiem, czy się uda.
But if everything goes well, I think I can ask about quitting.
Jeśli wszystko pójdzie dobrze, postaram się odejść.
I'd also make a ton of money,
Zarobię mnóstwo forsy,
so we'd be all right for a while even after I quit.
więc na jakiś czas wystarczy.
How much?
Ile?
Around ten million yen.
Jakieś dziesięć milionów.
Fine.
W porządku.
Maybe I can help.
Mogę ci pomóc.
What?
Co?
You're going to reach your goal and then cut ties with those people?
Chcesz osiągnąć cel i zerwać z nimi kontakt?
Respond!
Odpowiedz!
Yes.
Tak.
ASSESSMENT SHEET NAOMI KOBAYASHI
ARKUSZ OCENY NAOMI KOBAYASHI
Mom leaked information from her workplace to me.
Mama wykradła dane ze swojej pracy.
EPISODE 6
ODCINEK 6
The elderly people's assets, whether or not they have money,
Majątek starszych osób, posiadana gotówka,
their family details,
dane krewnych,
and even information about previous clients.
nawet dane poprzednich klientów.
I have to pee!
Muszę siku!
I'm coming!
Idę!
All right, I'm coming.
Już idę.
All right, hold on to my arms.
Proszę mnie chwycić.
Okay, come on.
Idziemy.
Hey, hey!
Proszę pana!
I don't know what it was that drove Mom to help me.
Nie wiem, dlaczego mama mi pomogła.
Now I have to take this information and transform it into money.
Muszę wykorzystać te informacje i zarobić pieniądze.
That's my mission.
To moja misja.
I call this the M register
Nazwałem to Rejestrem M,
because both "Mom" and "Makoto" begin with the letter M.
bo na tę literę zaczynają się słowa „mama” i „Makoto”.
Starting today, we'll be using this register as well.
Od dziś korzystamy też z tego rejestru.
Just like the new register, this is for internal use only.
Ten również jest tylko dla nas.
Don't tell anyone about its existence.
Nikomu o nim ani słowa.
Not even Dokugawa-san or Kanbe-san.
Nawet panom Dokugawie i Kanbemu.
What? Why?
Dlaczego?
I came up with this one on my own.
Sam go załatwiłem.
I'll explain to our superiors later.
Później im to wyjaśnię.
Dokugawa-san will kill you if you do something stupid.
Dokugawa cię zabije, jeśli zrobisz coś głupiego.
Let's focus on the sales.
Skupmy się na wynikach.
This smells like trouble...
Wyczuwam kłopoty.
Where did you get it?
Skąd to masz?
I have my ways.
Mam swoje dojścia.
This is a jackpot!
Rany, skarbnica!
It even says how bad their dementia is.
Nawet opisali stopień demencji.
This is going to save us!
Jesteśmy uratowani!
I'll take this for myself!
Biorę go!
-Aren't you afraid of Dokugawa-san? -Give it!
- Przecież boisz się Dokugawy. - Dawaj!
-Give it to me! -Wait a sec.
- Daj! - Czekaj.
I said wait!
Zaczekaj!
Wait, wait, wait! Calm down!
Chwilę, spokojnie!
Let's talk about how we'll do this.
Zastanówmy się, jak to rozegrać.
Right. We need to split it up fairly.
Musimy go uczciwie podzielić.
We'll draw straws.
Ciągnijmy słomki.
He's already got it.
Już wziął.
We'll draw straws for how many pages.
Wylosujemy strony.
-Here. -I've got it.
- Trzymaj. - Mam.
Excuse me! What happened here?
Przepraszam, co się stało?
I'm a homecare worker here.
Pracuję tu jako opiekunka.
Really?
Naprawdę?
It's terrible, the old man who lives here was the victim of a scam!
Ten starszy pan padł ofiarą oszustwa!
Scam?
Oszustwa?
What was his hair like?
Proszę opisać jego włosy.
He gave money to a young guy who came to his house.
Jakiś chłopak przyszedł po pieniądze.
It's unbelievable!
Nie do wiary!
To think he had millions in cash.
Pomyśleć, że trzymał w domu miliony.
The elderly are rich nowadays.
Bogaci ci staruszkowie.
Why'd he hand it over, I wonder?
Ale dlaczego dał mu pieniądze?
You'd think he'd know better.
Kto by się spodziewał.
The M register was more effective than I ever imagined.
Rejestr M był niezwykle skuteczny.
I feel bad for him. Kind of.
Szkoda mi go. Trochę.
Understood. We'll send one of our people to your house.
Rozumiem. Wyślemy kogoś.
Yes.
Tak.
Please have the money on hand, in cash.
Proszę przekazać kwotę w gotówce.
Thank you very much.
Dziękuję.
This is crazy.
Wariactwo.
Hello, Dokugawa-san?
Panie Dokugawa.
We've got another hit. Can you send the money collectors?
Kolejny ustrzelony. Wyśle pan kogoś po forsę?
Hey. Do you have a moment to meet up?
Masz chwilę?
Sure. And the money collectors?
Tak. A kurierzy?
I'll drive over now. I'll be there in ten.
Już jadę. Daj mi dziesięć minut.
What is it? What's wrong?
Coś nie tak?
It's nothing.
Nic.
I'm stepping out for a sec.
Muszę na chwilę wyjść.
We can't collect?
Nie odbierzemy kasy?
Yamada disappeared, and now we don't have enough money collectors.
Yamada zniknął, brakuje nam kurierów.
Even if we fool our targets,
Nawet jak oszukamy cel,
there's no one to go collect or take out the money.
nie ma kto odebrać gotówki.
There are stores that have lost up to 20 million yen.
Niektóre oddziały straciły po 20 baniek.
That much?
Aż tyle?
Seimiya's hit just now was also a bust.
Z celu Seimiyi też nic nie będzie.
So...
Czyli...
There's nothing we can do!
Nic nie możemy zrobić.
Don't tell the others about this.
Nie mów pozostałym.
It'll ruin their motivation.
Stracą motywację.
So what happens to our profits?
Co z naszym zyskiem?
In situations like this, the leader has to fill in the gaps.
Lider odpowiada za podwładnych.
So, Kanbe-san will pay himself?
Pan Kanbe sam zapłaci?
That's the rule.
Takie są zasady.
Kanbe-san is talking to our financiers about what needs to be done.
Omawia dalsze kroki z księgowymi.
Until you receive orders, hold off on going after big targets.
Dopóki nie dostaniecie rozkazu, unikajcie większych celów.
Go after small and new targets.
Atakujcie mniejsze i nowe.
Got it?
Zrozumiano?
Yes.
Tak.
Okay, okay.
Dobrze.
Don't worry. I'll introduce you to some money collectors.
Spokojnie, przedstawię pana kurierom.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
Hey, call Tecchan.
Zadzwoń do Tecchana.
Right away.
Tak jest.
I'll take care of it.
Zajmę się tym.
Thank you for your consideration. However...
Dziękuję za pomoc. Ale...
Actually, I know someone who might be good.
znam kogoś, kto się nada.
They can be trusted.
To zaufani ludzie.
Wait a moment.
Chwileczkę.
Are you saying you can't trust my people?
Nie ufa pan moim ludziom?
-Of course not-- -Why?
- Skądże... - Dlaczego?
Is it because I'm yakuza? You don't trust the yakuza?
Bo należę do yakuzy? Nie ufa pan nam?
Minegishi, what do you think?
Co ty na to, Minegishi?
It seems to me he's wary of you.
Wydaje mi się, że panu nie ufa.
Wary of me? Why would Kanbe-chan be wary of me?
Dlaczegóż to miałby mi nie ufać?
If he trusts people employed by the yakuza
Jeśli zaufa ludziom yakuzy,
and they run off with his money, he'll have nothing.
a oni uciekną z jego forsą, zostanie z niczym.
That's what he thinks.
Tak uważa.
Kanbe-chan, how dare you think such things?
Jak pan śmie, panie Kanbe?
-That's not it! -It'd better not be!
- To nie tak! - Oby.
Kanbe-chan, you don't have any other plans today, right?
Nie ma pan planów na dziś, prawda?
Let's go get something to eat.
Chodźmy coś zjeść.
Yes. Thank you.
Chętnie. Dziękuję.
We'll get yakiniku.
Zjemy yakiniku.
I see...
Rozumiem.
No money collectors...
Nie ma kurierów.
Don't tell the others.
Nie mów reszcie.
Sure...
Jasne.
But Kanbe-san can't cover the losses forever.
Kanbe nie będzie wiecznie płacił.
This is bad.
Kiepsko.
They're trying to solve it, though.
Szukają rozwiązania.
It's fine as long as we're paid,
To nic, dopóki nam płacą,
but if that's delayed, everyone's motivation will disappear.
ale jak przestaną, zespół straci motywację.
Yeah...
Tak.
But thanks for telling me.
Dzięki, że mi powiedziałeś.
I'll slow down my pace for now.
Trochę zwolnię.
Kurusu.
Kurusu.
I heard everything.
Wszystko słyszałem.
-Hey, don't tell-- -I got it.
- Nie mów... - Jasne.
I won't tell. But this is pretty bad, isn't it?
Nie powiem. Ale jest kiepsko, co?
If you're willing, I have a proposal...
Mam pewną propozycję.
Proposal?
Propozycję?
-I'm home. -Welcome back.
- Wróciłem. - Cześć.
That register is really helping.
Rejestr bardzo nam pomaga.
It's super effective. Everyone is amazed.
Wszyscy są w szoku.
Do you always feel like this?
Zawsze tak się czujesz?
What?
Jak?
I feel nauseous all the time.
Ciągle mam mdłości.
Makoto, have you been living like this all this time?
Też tak masz?
At first.
Na początku miałem.
But now I don't feel anything.
Teraz już nic nie czuję.
This is my job.
Taka praca.
Shall I get you some medicine?
Dać ci coś?
I'm fine. I'm just a little anxious.
Nie trzeba, po prostu się denerwuję.
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
I thought I had made up my mind.
Myślałam, że się z tym pogodziłam.
Dinner is in the fridge.
Obiad masz w lodówce.
Yeah.
Jasne.
-Hey.
- Cześć.
-Aren't you working today? -I'm off.
- Nie pracujesz dziś? - Nie.
Why? What's up?
Co się stało?
Hey...
Posłuchaj...
Did Sachiko-chan say anything to you?
Sachiko coś ci powiedziała?
Say anything? Like what?
Na przykład co?
She didn't ask?
Nie pytała,
About you doing some scary type of work or anything?
czy nie masz jakiejś strasznej pracy?
Oh, yeah. Himeka said something, right?
Himeka ci nagadała?
She was lying.
Kłamała.
Himeka was really scared.
Wystraszyła się.
Oh, really?
Serio?
Makoto!
Makoto!
I'm not lying.
Mówię prawdę.
I'm glad.
Cieszę się.
I was worried.
Martwiłam się.
-This way. -Okay.
- Tędy. - Jasne.
Hey!
Siema!
I brought him.
Przyprowadziłem go.
This is Taiga, and that's Shiro.
To jest Taiga, a to Shiro.
I met them when I worked at an escort agency.
Poznałem ich, jak pilnowałem panienek.
Hey.
Siema!
-This is great! -This is Kusano.
- Super! - To jest Kusano.
He's my boss!
To mój szef!
Hello.
Cześć.
Taiga.
Taiga.
Get yourself together, we have a guest!
Ogarnij się, mamy gościa!
Good afternoon.
Dzień dobry.
Hey, you want some hot pot?
Zjesz trochę?
We got the cabbage from a field nearby.
Zwinęliśmy kapustę z pobliskiego pola.
It's fresh and good.
Świeża, pyszna.
Idiot! That's Kuru-chan's boss, did you hear?
To szef Kurusu, kretynie!
He's an important guy!
Szycha!
We can't just offer him weed.
Nie dawaj mu zieleniny.
Some live seafood will be here soon.
Zaraz będą owoce morza.
Hey!
Siema!
There he is!
No, jest!
They're huge!
Ale olbrzymy!
Look at them move!
Ale mają ruchy.
It got my finger!
Dziabnął mnie!
It got me again!
Znowu!
Hello there. My name is Toki.
Cześć, nazywam się Toki.
I got these guys from the sewer over there.
Wyciągnąłem je z kanałów.
Please have some.
Częstuj się.
Yes, please have some.
Smacznego.
This is where they live. You can tell they're tough.
Mieszkają tu. Twardziele.
You were arrested recently, right?
Ostatnio cię aresztowali, nie?
That was rough.
Gruba akcja.
I told the dude to hit me again.
Powiedziałem typowi, żeby znów mnie walnął.
And he was like...
A on na to...
"You want to go again? Really?"
„Znowu chcesz oberwać?¨.
That's what he said to me!
Tak powiedział.
We want to get promoted to the top!
Pniemy się na szczyt!
Yeah!
Tak!
They've got spirit, right?
Mają ambicje, co?
Right?
Prawda?
If you pay us, we'll do whatever you want.
Za kasę zrobimy wszystko.
The old people in Tokyo
Dziadki w Tokio
-have tons of money, right? -They're loaded!
- mają kupę forsy, nie? - Masę!
For a 100 million...
Za sto milionów...
One hundred million?
Sto baniek?
I would commit murder, burn down houses.
Mogę zabijać i palić domy.
It's all the same to me!
Ja tak samo!
It's all the same!
Tak samo!
Come on.
Chodź.
What?
Co?
No way.
Nie ma mowy.
Why?
Czemu?
-They'd make perfect collectors. -It's too dangerous.
- Nadają się na kurierów. - Zbyt duże ryzyko.
-They're crazy. -What?
- To wariaci. - Co?
They're perfect!
Są idealni!
They're like cavemen.
To dzikusy.
I can't introduce them to our superiors. I'm going home.
Nie przedstawię ich szefostwu. Spadam.
Wait.
Zaczekaj.
Apologize.
Przeproś.
What?
Co?
Don't talk down to my friends. Apologize!
Nie mów tak o moich kolegach. Przeproś!
No...
Nie...
I didn't mean to...
Nie chciałem...
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
I'm...
Bardzo...
sorry.
przepraszam.
Hey, Kusano...
Kusano.
I can't stand how you act like you're better than everyone.
Uważasz się za lepszego od nas.
So you went to college?
Studiowałeś?
You worked at a real job?
Miałeś normalną pracę?
I don't know what it is,
Nie wiem dlaczego,
but I just can't stand you.
ale po prostu cię nie znoszę.
If you keep acting all high and mighty, you might get stabbed in the back.
Dalej pusz się jak paw, to ktoś wbije ci nóż w plecy.
Stabbed?
Nóż?
That's right.
Tak.
By who?
Niby kto?
"By who"?
Co?
It was hypothetical. Don't take it so seriously.
Mówię hipotetycznie. Nie przejmuj się.
They got together on their day off for us.
Przyszli tu specjalnie dla nas.
They'll be pissed if we don't accept their hospitality.
Wkurzą się, jak nie damy się ugościć.
Come on.
Chodź.
Come on!
No chodź!
Sorry, guys.
Wybaczcie.
Let him try some of that.
Dajcie mu trochę.
It's good, right?
Dobre, co?
Let him eat!
Niech je!
Good morning.
Dzień dobry.
This sucks.
Do bani.
Where's the money?
Gdzie forsa?
Kuru-chan is going to get mad at us again.
Kuru znowu się wścieknie.
He is really scary when he gets mad.
Przeraża mnie wtedy.
Hello!
Dzień dobry!
It's Sachiko from the home helper service.
Tu Sachiko, opiekunka.
Hello?
Halo?
Yabe-san?
Panie Yabe?
How are you doing?
Wszystko dobrze?
Yabe-san! Are you all right?
Nic panu nie jest?
No! Stop! What are you doing?
Nie! Przestańcie! Co wy robicie?
Stop!
Przestańcie!
Don't!
Nie!
-Let me go! -Shut up!
- Puśćcie mnie! - Morda!
Mom?
Mamo?
I'm Kanazaki from the Takata Police Station.
Kanazaki, policja w Takata.
We just heard about what happened from your mother.
Słyszeliśmy, co spotkało pana mamę.
Is she badly hurt?
Jest poważnie ranna?
You should go see her and help her calm down.
Proszę do niej iść i ją uspokoić.
Who did this?
Kto za tym stoi?
We don't know yet.
Jeszcze nie wiemy.
We'll visit her again soon to talk more. If you need anything, call us.
Wrócimy do państwa. W razie czego proszę dzwonić.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
Mom...
Mamo...
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Napisy: Konrad Szabowicz